Guide to the Cornell Nursery School records,1920-1970.
Cornell Nursery School records, 1920-1970
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Cornell Nursery School records, 1920-1970.
23-13-2365
New York State College of Home Economics. Cornell Nursery School.
29.6 Cubic Feet.
Administrative records, student records, articles, course materials and curricula, photographs, films, scrapbooks, books, toys.
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Nursery School records, ca. 1920-1970; Nursery School administrative records, ca. 1920-1950; and Family Life class student reports, 1940s.
ORGANIZATIONAL HISTORY
In 1925 the Department of Family Life was organized and in 1945 the name was changed to the Department of Child Development and Family Relationships. In 1969 the name changed to Human Development and Family Studies, and during the 1998-99 year it was shortened to Human Development.
COLLECTION DESCRIPTION
Nursery School records, ca. 1920-1970; Nursery School administrative records, ca. 1920-1950; and Family Life class student reports, 1940s. Includes photographs of various activities in the Nursery School from 1920-1979, a scrapbook describing all aspects of the Nursery School in the 1930's, wooden puzzles produced by Milton Bradley that were presented yearly, and "Domecon" baby books from the 1920s. Also a film showing a nursery school, bathing cute baby; Library Tower; Students on quadrangle; alumni reunion; singing on steps of Goldwin Smith; feeding baby. about 1930, it is unclear if this film is from this collection and whether it shows the Cornell Nursery School.
SUBJECTS
Names:
New York State College of Home Economics.; Davey, Alice Jeanette, 1924-.; Milton Bradley Company.; New York State College of Home Economics. Dept. of Family Life.; New York State College of Home Economics. Dept. of Child Development and Family Relationships.; New York State College of Human Ecology.; New York State College of Human Ecology. Dept. of Human Development and Family Studies.; New York State College of Human Ecology. Dept. of Human Development.
Subjects:
Nursery schools--New York (State)--Ithaca.; Children.; Education, Preschool.; Family--Study and teaching.; Family--Research.; Home economics--Study and teaching.; Wooden toys.
Form and Genre Terms:
Lantern slides.; Photographs.; Scrapbooks.; Motion pictures (visual works).
INFORMATION FOR USERS
Access Restrictions:
Boxes 1-25, Box 27 Folders 1-19 and 26-32, Box 32, and Box 37 are restricted until 2082, except with permission from the University Archivist, with no personal identifying information of students being used.
RELATED MATERIALS
The films Practice Babies and Nursery School from this collection have been digitized and can be found on Cornell's Library Media Space website along with other Home Economics and related films.
SERIES LIST
Series I. Nursery School Student Records
Boxes 1-25 and 37
Series II. Correspondence
Box 26 - folders 1-13
Series III. Nursery School Information: Curriculum, Programs, Publications
Box 24, Box 26- folders 14-52, Box 27
Series IV. Photographs and Films
Boxes 28-31, 33 and 34
Series V. Scrapbook, Baby Books, Toys
Boxes 31, 35 and 36
CONTAINER LIST
- Series I: Nursery School - Student Records - Restricted
  - A-Bon, 1920-1969 (Box 1)
  - Bon-Cha, 1920-1969 (Box 2)
  - Chi - Fi, 1920-1969 (Box 3)
  - Fi-Hen, 1920-1969 (Box 4)
  - Her-Jan, 1920-1969 (Box 5)
  - Jen-Kle, 1920-1969 (Box 6)
  - Lon-Mat, 1920-1969 (Box 7)
  - Mat-Mot, 1920-1969 (Box 8)
  - Mot-Ove, 1920-1969 (Box 9)
  - Ot-Rai, 1920-1969 (Box 10)
  - Rai-Sal, 1920-1969 (Box 11)
  - Sal-Smi, 1920-1969 (Box 12)
  - Smi-Ter, 1920-1969 (Box 13)
  - Tha-Web, 1920-1969 (Box 14)
  - Wel-Z, 1920-1969 (Box 15)
  - not alphabetical, 1965-1975 (Box 16-18)
  - not alphabetical and F-Gre from the 1920-1939, 1965-1975 (Box 19)
  - Gre-Ha, 1920-1939 (Box 20)
  - not alphabetical, 1960-1969 (Box 21)
  - Staff Records (Box 22)
  - Parents Meetings, Monday Council Reports, Records on students who attended the nursery school, 1930-1939 (Box 23)
  - Student Histories of College students who enrolled in Family Life Courses-100, 220 and 330-arranged alphabetically, 1940-1949 (Box 25)
  - Observations of nursery school children done by students when Katherine Reeves was the Director, 1950-1959 (Box 37)
- Series II: Correspondence
  - Katherine Reeves Correspondence, 1940-1943 (Box 26, Folder 1)
  - Katherine Reeves Correspondence, 1939-1940 (Box 26, Folder 2)
  - Katherine Reeves Correspondence, 1938-1939 (Box 26, Folder 3)
  - Katherine Reeves Correspondence, 1937-1938 (Box 26, Folder 4)
  - Katherine Reeves Correspondence, 1939 (Box 26, Folder 5)
  - Katherine Reeves Correspondence, 1937 (Box 26, Folder 6)
  - Katherine Reeves Correspondence, 1936 (Box 26, Folder 7)
  - Katherine Reeves Correspondence, 1935 (Box 26, Folder 8)
  - Katherine Reeves Correspondence, 1934 (Box 26, Folder 9)
  - Katherine Reeves Correspondence, 1930-1933 (Box 26, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence - Visiting Groups, 1936-1937 (Box 26, Folder 11)
  - Correspondence - Katherine Reeves - Sabbatic, 1940 (Box 26, Folder 12)
  - Correspondence - Freshman orientation, 1939-1942 (Box 26, Folder 13)
- Series III: Nursery School Information: Curriculum, Programs, Publications- Partially Restricted
  - Child Training and Nursery School Annual Reports, 1925-1927 (Box 35, Folder 1)
  - Nursery school children observations and parent interviews, 1931-1940 (Box 24)
  - Monday Council, 1930-1932 (Box 24)
  - Home visitation reports, 1949-1951 (Box 24)
  - "Democracy Begins at Home", 1940 (Box 26, Folder 14)
  - Plans for play group - summer school, 1939 (Box 26, Folder 15)
  - Manuscripts of articles and talks (Box 26, Folder 16)
  - Material for talks (Box 26, Folder 17)
  - Family Morale and National Strength (Box 26, Folder 18)
  - Family Life Conference, 1940 (Box 26, Folder 19)
  - Family Counseling Program, 1937 (Box 26, Folder 20)
  - Integrated Course - Economics of the Household (Box 26, Folder 21)
  - Publicity Committee - ACE, 1936-1937 (Box 26, Folder 22)
  - Affiliations Committee - New York State - Childhood Education (Inactive) (Box 26, Folder 23)
  - Literature Committee - ACE, 1936-1937 (Box 26, Folder 24)
  - Records for Albany - Miss Beebe's Curriculum (Box 26, Folder 25)
  - Pi Lambda Theta - Katherine Reeves, 1937 (Box 26, Folder 26)
  - Religious Education (Box 26, Folder 27)
  - Association for Childhood Education, 1933-1934 (Box 26, Folder 28)
  - Joyce Jones - Cornell, 1934 (Box 26, Folder 29)
  - Housekeeper's Duties (Box 26, Folder 30)
  - Educational Policies, 1939 (Box 26, Folder 31)
  - The Association for Arts in Childhood (Box 26, Folder 32)
  - American Library Association, 1940 (Box 26, Folder 33)
  - Seminar on the Young Child and the Family (Box 26, Folder 34)
  - Summer session, 1940 (Box 26, Folder 35)
  - Study of Summer Session (Box 26, Folder 36)
  - Home Economics Curriculum, 1940-1941 (Box 26, Folder 37)
  - Dionne Quintuplets Research Conference, 1937 (Box 26, Folder 38)
  - Students interested in Assistantships in summer school laboratories, 1937 (Box 26, Folder 39)
  - Family Life 220 - Evaluation reports (Box 26, Folder 40)
  - Participation material from other centers (Box 26, Folder 41)
  - Mimeographed material (Box 26, Folder 42)
  - Study Club letters, 1937-1938 (Box 26, Folder 43)
  - Language development (Box 26, Folder 44)
  - Sampling of Extension material, 1933-1937 (Box 26, Folder 45)
  - Sampling of Extension material, 1933-1936 (Box 26, Folder 46)
  - Sampling of Extension material, 1930-1934 (Box 26, Folder 46A)
  - Seminar in Home Economics Education, 1936 (Box 26, Folder 47)
  - School visiting, 1938 (Box 26, Folder 48)
  - The Child - published by the Children's Bureau, 1938 (Box 26, Folder 49)
  - Food and Nutrition - 131, 1927-1930 (Box 26, Folder 50)
  - Pamphlets (Box 26, Folder 51)
  - Curriculum Organization - Dr. Bonser (Box 26, Folder 52)
  - Nursery School Correspondence - A-Z, 1933-1946 (Box 27, Folder 1-19)
  - Home Nursing and Homemaking - syllabus (Box 27, Folder 20)
  - Home Nursing and Home Hygiene - syllabus (Box 27, Folder 21)
  - Home Economics - Sr. High School Curriculum (Box 27, Folder 22)
  - Dr. Spafford's Notes, 1938 (Box 27, Folder 23)
  - Foods and Nutrition Material (Box 27, Folder 24)
  - Problems for Parent Educators - edited by Flora Thurston, 1929-1930 (Box 27, Folder 25)
  - Nursery School Enrollment, 1930-1949 (Box 27, Folder 26)
  - Nursery School Enrollment, 1920-1959 (Box 27, Folder 27)
  - Enrollment, 1940-1941 (Box 27, Folder 28)
  - Enrollment, 1941-1942 (Box 27, Folder 29)
  - Enrollment, 1934-1953 (Box 27, Folder 30)
  - Enrollment - summer session, 1935-1950 (Box 27, Folder 31)
  - Nursery School Lists, 1970-1979 (Box 27, Folder 32)
  - Child Development - Iowa State College (Box 27, Folder 33)
  - Committee on Minimum Essentials, 1934 (Box 27, Folder 34)
  - Minimum Essentials - building, 1934 (Box 27, Folder 35)
  - Parent - Child Self Study Card (Box 27, Folder 36)
  - Music Questionnaires - Helen Murray, 1950 (Box 27, Folder 37)
  - Menus, 1945-1946 (Box 27, Folder 38)
  - Menus, 1946-1947 (Box 27, Folder 39)
  - Menus, 1949-1950 (Box 27, Folder 40)
  - Menus, 1950-1952 (Box 27, Folder 41)
  - Menus, 1944-1945 (Box 27, Folder 42)
  - Nursery School Schedules, 1937-1947 (Box 27, Folder 43)
  - Sample Form Letters, 1930-1959 (Box 27, Folder 44)
  - Correspondence Concerning Miss Webber, 1937 (Box 27, Folder 45)
  - Nursery School Staff - Records and Reports (Box 27, Folder 46)
  - Licences of Nursery School, 1926-1933 (Box 27, Folder 47)
  - Course Evaluations - Family Life 100 (Box 27, Folder 48-49)
  - Home Economics Student Faculty Committee, 1952-1957 (Box 27, Folder 50)
  - Family Life Course Material, 1930-1939 (Box 27, Folder 51-53)
  - Family Life 100 - Suggestions and Criticisms, 1935-1936 (Box 27, Folder 54)
  - Family Life 100 - Criticisms (Box 27, Folder 55-56)
  - Summer Parents' Meeting, 1930 (Box 27, Folder 57)
  - Memoranda to Parents (Box 27, Folder 58)
- Series IV: Nursery School: Photographs and Films
  - Folder from the Cornell Chapter of the American Association of University Professors and index cards with nursery school expenditures listed, 1930-1939 (Box 28)
  - Photograph album of Miss Reeves' students working with nursery school children, 1929-1930 (Box 28)
  - 16 mm Films-Black and white film of back yard play group (Summer 1939) use DVD #142; one color film of backyard play group (summer of 1939) use DVD #145; Troy Studies - baby in high chair, playpen (1928) use DVD #143; film from D.D. Scarborough (October 1929) use DVD #144, 1928-1939 (Box 28)
  - Silent color film of students playing at the Cornell Nursery School. (Use DVD-1006 in same box.), c.1940; F-824 (Box 28)
  - Silent color film of students playing at the Cornell Nursery School - copy of film F-824, 1940; DVD-1006 (Box 28)
    Click here to see a digitized version of the film.
  - Various photographs and negatives and glass negatives of nursery school children, 1920-1939 (Box 28)
  - Use DVD-764. Film showing a nursery school, bathing cute baby; Library Tower; Students on quadrangle; alumni reunion; singing on steps of Goldwin Smith; feeding baby. About 1930, it is unclear if this film is from this collection and whether it shows the Cornell Nursery School., F-40
  - Copy of Film F-40, DVD-764 (Box 28)
  - Practice Babies - Domecon babies. (Use DVD-1010 in same box.), 1938; F-178 (Box 28)
    Home Economics students with babies and children.
  - Practice Babies - Domecon babies - copy of Film F-178, DVD-1010 (Box 28)
  - Photographs (Box 29)
  - Lantern Slides (Box 30)
  - Negatives and glass slides (Box 33, Folder 1)
  - Nursery School Activities Photographs (10 of them): Childhood Education September Issue; Lunchtime - April 20, 1926 with Karl Von Bug, Rodney Kearl, David Levine, Janet Carson, Rand Wilson, Elizabeth Wilson, Steven Schwartz and Jeanne Specht (2 copies); Tarri Balhell, Lynne Munschauer, Karl Von Bug, Rodney Kearl at the Nursery School, May 23, 1957; Kim O'Conner, Rodney Kearl and Scott Partridge, May 24, 1957; Lynne Munschauer, Jacie Balliett, Patricia Hughes, Jean Anderson (participating student), Peter Campbell, Janet Corson and Steven Schwartz (Box 33, Folder 2)
  - Nursery School Children - 18 photographs, including Peter Racedalph, 1943 (Box 33, Folder 3)
  - Nursery School Activities - various years: 20 photographs, including 15 contact sheets (Box 33, Folder 4)
  - Nursery School Activities - various years: 8 photographs, 2 photos dated July 9, 1970 (Box 33, Folder 5)
  - Outdoor Activities - 13 photographs including photographs of playground equipment from Child-Life and Play Speciality Association, Hollistor, Massachusetts (Box 33, Folder 6)
  - Outdoor Activities - 25 Photos (Box 33, Folder 7)
  - Outdoor Activities - 28 photos, including Lois Ann at 2½ thumb tacking her paper to an easel and a photo of George Washington Chang at the Nursery School, that was used in the Post Standard, July 16, 1944 (Box 33, Folder 8)
  - Outdoor Activities: 24 photos, including John Leete Stule and Ann Leete Wheeler, riding tricycles (Box 33, Folder 9)
  - Outdoor Activities: 10 photos (Box 33, Folder 10)
  - Outdoor Activities: early years, 15 photos (Box 33, Folder 11)
  - Nursery School Facility: 12 photos (Box 33, Folder 12)
  - Indoor Activities: various years, 15 photos (Box 33, Folder 13)
  - Indoor Activities: various years, 20 photos (Box 33, Folder 14)
  - Eating Activities: various years, 23 photos (Box 33, Folder 15)
  - Nursery School Groups of students and teachers: 18 photos (Box 33, Folder 16)
  - Nursery School Hygiene: various years, 16 photos (Box 33, Folder 17)
  - Photos of Jennifer Birckmayer, Director of the Nursery School, 1957 (Box 34, Folder 1)
  - Nursery School Activities: 35 photos (Box 34, Folder 2-6)
  - Nursery School Negatives (Box 34, Folder 7-8)
  - Photographs (Box 34, Folder 9-11)
  - Negatives (Box 34, Folder 12)
- Series V: Scrapbook, Baby Books, Toys
  - Domecon Baby Books, 1921-1926 (Box 31)
  - Information About the twins, Mary Alice and Rose Ann and Baby Sheila, 1937, 1948-1950 (Box 31)
  - Oversized scrapbook describing the early days of the Nursery School, 1930-1949 (Box 35)
  - Wooden gift toys and tru-tone, no-roll crayons all produced by the Milton Bradley Company (Box 36)